I'd like to apologize, first of all, to all of you
أود أن أعتذر، أولا وقبل كل شيء، لكم جميعا
because I have no form
لأنه ليس لدي أي شكل من أشكال
of PowerPoint presentation.
عروض باور بوينت.
So what I'm going to do
وبالتالي ما سأقوم به
is, every now and again, I will make this gesture,
هو، أنه بين حين وآخر، سأقوم بهذه الحركة،
and in a moment of PowerPoint democracy,
وفي لحظة من ديموقراطية الباور بوينت،
you can imagine what you'd like to see.
يمكنكم تخير ما تريدون رؤيته.
I do a radio show.
أقدم برنامجا إذاعيا.
The radio show is called "The Infinite Monkey Cage."
البرنامج الإذاعي يدعى "قفص القرد اللامنتهي."
It's about science, it's about rationalism.
يتعلق بالعلم، والعقلانية.
So therefore, we get a lot of complaints
وبالتالي، تأتينا شكاوى كثيرة
every single week --
في كل أسبوع --
complaints including one we get very often,
شكاوى من بينها واحدة نتلقاها باستمرار،
which is to say the very title, "Infinite Monkey Cage,"
والتي هي القول بأن العنوان بحد ذاته، "قفص القرد اللامنتهي،"
celebrates the idea of vivisection.
يصفق لفكرة تشريح الأحياء.
We have made it quite clear to these people
وقد وضحنا لهؤلاء الناس
that an infinite monkey cage is roomy.
أن قفص قرد لامنته فسيح للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We also had someone else who said,
وقد جاءنا كذلك من قال،
"'The Infinite Monkey Cage' idea is ridiculous.
"فكرة قفص القرد اللامنتهي سخيفة.
An infinite number of monkeys
عدد لا منته من القرود
could never write the works of Shakespeare.
لا يمكنه أبدا أن يكتب أعمال شكسبير.
We know this because they did an experiment."
نعرف ذلك لأنهم قاموا بتجربة."
Yes, they gave 12 monkeys a typewriter for a week,
نعم، أعطوا 12 قردا آلة كاتبة لأسبوع،
and after a week, they only used it as a bathroom.
وبعد أسبوع، استعملوها فقط كمرحاض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the main element though, the main complaint we get --
والعنصر الآساسي مع ذلك، الشكوى الرئيسية التي تأتينا --
and one that I find most worrying --
والتي أجدها أكثر إثارة للقلق --
is that people say, "Oh, why do you insist
هو أن الناس يقولون، "أوه، لماذا تصر
on ruining the magic?
على إفساد السحر؟
You bring in science, and it ruins the magic."
تأتي بالعلم، فيفسد السحر."
Now I'm an arts graduate;
الآن أنا متخرج من تخصص الفنون؛
I love myth and magic
أحب السحر والأسطورة
and existentialism and self-loathing.
والوجودية والإشمئزاز الذاتي.
That's what I do.
هذا ما أقوم به.
But I also don't understand
لكنني كذلك لا أفهم
how it does ruin the magic.
كيف يفسد ذلك السحر.
All of the magic, I think,
كل السحر، أعتقد،
that may well be taken away by science
الذي قد يزال من طرف العلم
is then replaced by something as wonderful.
تعوض إذن بشيء بنفس القدر من الروعة.
Astrology, for instance:
علم التنجيم، مثلا:
like many rationalists, I'm a Pisces.
مثل الكثير من العقلانيين، أنا من برج الحوت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now astrology --
الآن التنجيم --
we remove the banal idea
نزيل الفكرة البديهية
that your life could be predicted;
أن حياتك يمكن التنبؤ بها؛
that you'll, perhaps today, meet a lucky man
أنه ربما تلتقي اليوم برجل محظوظ
who's wearing a hat.
يرتدي قبعة.
That is gone.
هذا قد ولى.
But if we want to look at the sky and see predictions, we still can.
لكن إن أردنا النظر إلى السماء ورؤية التنبؤات، لا يزال بإمكاننا ذلك.
We can see predictions of galaxies forming,
يمكننا أن نرى تنبؤات بتكون المجرات،
of galaxies colliding into each other, of new solar systems.
بتصادم المجرات، بأنظمة شمسية جديدة.
This is a wonderful thing.
هذا أمر رائع.
If the Sun could one day -- and indeed the Earth, in fact --
إن استطاعت الشمس يوما ما -- والأرض بالفعل، في الحقيقة --
if the Earth could read its own astrological, astronomical chart,
إن استطاعت الأرض قراءة رموزها الفلكية، مخططاتها الفلكية،
one day it would say,
ستقول يوما ما،
"Not a good day for making plans.
"ليس يوما مناسبا للتخطيط.
You'll been engulfed by a red giant."
سيتم اجتياحها بعملاق أحمر."
And that to me as well,
وهذا بالنسبة لي كذلك،
that if you think I'm worried about losing worlds,
أنه إن اعتقدتم أنني خائف من فقدان العوالم،
well Many Worlds theory --
حسنا نظرية العوالم المتعددة --
one of the most beautiful, fascinating,
واحدة من أجمل وأروع
sometimes terrifying ideas
وأحيانا أرعب الأفكار
from the quantum interpretation --
من ناحية تفسير الكم --
is a wonderful thing.
هو أمر مذهل.
That every person here, every decision that you've made today,
أن كل شخص هنا، كل قرار اتخذتموه اليوم،
every decision you've made in your life,
كل قرار اتخذتوه في حياتكم،
you've not really made that decision,
لم تقوموا بالفعل باتخاذه،
but in fact, every single permutation of those decisions
لكن في الواقع، كل تبدل لتلك القرارات
is made, each one going off into a new universe.
قد تم اتخاذه، كل منها موجه في كون جديد.
That is a wonderful idea.
تلك فكرة مذهلة.
If you ever think that your life is rubbish,
إن فكرتم قط أن الحياة سخيفة،
always remember
تذكروا دائما
there's another you that's made much worse decisions than that.
أنه هناك نسخة منك قد اتخذت قرارات أكثر سوء من ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you ever think, "Ah, I want to end it all,"
إن فكرتم قط، "أه، أريد إنهاء كل شيء،"
don't end it all.
لا تنهوا كل شيء.
Remember that in the majority of universes,
تذكروا أنه في معظم الأكوان،
you don't even exist in the first place.
لستم موجودين حتى أصلا.
This to me, in its own strange way,
هذا بالنسبة لي، بغرابته،
is very, very comforting.
هو أمر مريح للغاية.
Now reincarnation, that's another thing gone -- the afterlife.
الآن التناسخ، ذاك أمر آخر قد ذهب -- ما بعد الحياة.
But it's not gone.
لكنه لم يذهب.
Science actually says
العلم في الواقع يقول
we will live forever.
أننا سنعيش للأبد.
Well, there is one proviso.
حسنا، هناك تحفظ واحد.
We won't actually live forever. You won't live forever.
لن نعيش في الوقع إلى الأبد. لن تعيش إلى الأبد.
Your consciousness, the you-ness of you, the me-ness of me --
إدراكك، ذاتك، وأناك --
that gets this one go.
كلها تحصل على هذه الدفعة.
But every single thing that makes us,
لكن كل شيء يكوننا،
every atom in us,
كل ذرة فينا،
has already created a myriad of different things
قد شكلت ما لا يعد ولا يحصى من الأشياء المختلفة
and will go on to create a myriad of new things.
وستستمر في إنشاء ما لا يعد ولا يحصى من الأشياء الجديدة.
We have been mountains
قد كنا جبالا
and apples and pulsars
وتفاحات ونجوما نابضة
and other people's knees.
وركب أشخاص آخرين.
Who knows, maybe one of your atoms was once Napoleon's knee.
من يدري، ربما تكون إحدى ذراتك جزء من ركبة نابليون.
That is a good thing.
ذاك أمر جيد.
Unlike the occupants of the universe,
على خلاف مستوطنيه،
the universe itself is not wasteful.
الكون في ذاته ليس مبذرا.
We are all totally recyclable.
كلنا قابلون لإعادة التدوير.
And when we die,
وحين نموت،
we don't even have to be placed in different refuse sacs.
ليس علينا حتى أن نوجد في أكياس مهملات مختلفة.
This is a wonderful thing.
هذا أمر مذهل.
Understanding, to me,
الفهم، بالنسبة لي،
does not remove the wonder and the joy.
لا يزيل الذهول والبهجة.
For instance, my wife could turn to me and she may say,
على سبيل المثال، قد تلتفت إلي زوجتي وتقول،
"Why do you love me?"
"لماذا تحبني؟"
And I can with all honesty
ويمكنني وبكل صدق
look her in the eye and say,
أن أنظر إلى عينيها وأقول،
"Because our pheromones
"لأن هرموناتنا
matched our olfactory receptors."
طابقت مستقبلاتنا الشمية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Though I'll probably also say something
لكن ربما سأقول شيئا
about her hair and personality as well.
بخصوص شعرها وشخصيتها كذلك.
And that is a wonderful thing there.
وذاك أمر مذهل.
Love does not die because of that thing.
الحب لا يموت بسبب ذلك.
Pain doesn't go away either.
الألم لا يزول كذلك.
This is a terrible thing, even though I understand pain.
هذا أمر فظيع، على الرغم من أنني أفهم الألم.
If someone punches me --
إن لكمني أحدهم --
and because of my personality,
وبسبب شخصيتي،
this is recently a regular occurrence --
صار حدثا عاديا مؤخرا --
I understand where the pain comes from.
أعي من أين يأتي الألم.
It is basically momentum to energy
إنه أساسا قوة الدفع على الطاقة
where the four-vector is constant -- that's what it is.
حيث أن المتجهات الأربعة ثابتة -- هذا ما هو عليه.
But at no point can I react and go,
لكنني لن أرد أبدا وأقول،
"Ha! Is that the best momentum-to-energy fourth vector constant you've got?"
"أها! هل تلك أفضل متجهة رابعة لقوة دفع على الطاقة لديك؟"
No, I just spit out a tooth.
لا، فقط أبصق سنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that is all of these different things -- the love for my child.
وتلك هي كل هذه الأشياء المختلفة -- حبي لطفلي.
I have a son. His name is Archie.
لدي ابن. اسمه أرتشي.
I'm very lucky,
أنا جد محظوظ،
because he's better than all the other children.
لأنه أفضل من كل الأطفال الآخرين.
Now I know you don't think that.
الآن أعرف أنكم لا تعتقدون ذلك.
You may well have your own children
قد يكون لديكم طفل
and think, "Oh no, my child's best."
وتعتقدون، "أوه لا، طفلي هو الأفضل."
That's the wonderful thing about evolution --
هذا هو المذهل بخصوص التطور --
the predilection to believe
الولع بالاعتقاد
that our child is best.
أن أطفالنا هم الأفضل.
Now in many ways, that's just a survival thing.
الآن بطرق مختلفة، ذلك فقط مرتبط بالبقاء.
The fact we see here is the vehicle for our genes,
الحقيقة التي نراها هي محرك جيناتنا،
and therefore we love it.
وبالتالي نحبها.
But we don't notice that bit; we just unconditionally love.
لكننا لا نلاحظ ذلك الجزء؛ فقط نحب دون قيد أوشرط.
That is a wonderful thing.
ذاك أمر مذهل.
Though I should say that my son is best
رغم أنه يجب أن أقول أن ابني هو الأفضل
and is better than your children.
وأحسن من طفلكم.
I've done some tests.
أجريت بعض الاختبارات.
And all of these things to me
وكل هذه الأشياء بالنسبة لي
give such joy and excitement and wonder.
تعطي نوعا من البهجة والإثارة والدهشة.
Even quantum mechanics can give you an excuse
حتى ميكانيكا الكم يمكن أن تعطيكم عذرا
for bad housework, for instance.
لأعمال منزلية سيئة، على سبيل المثال.
Perhaps you've been at home for a week on your own.
ربما قد تكون في البيت لأسبوع لوحدك.
You house is in a terrible state.
بيتك في حالة رهيبة.
Your partner is about to return.
وشريكك على وشك العودة.
You think, what should I do?
تفكرون، ماذا يتوجب علي القيام به؟
Do nothing.
لا تقم بشيء.
All you have to do
كل ما يجب أن تقوم به
is, when she walks in, using a quantum interpretation,
هو، حين تدخل، استخدم التفسير الكمي،
say, "I'm so sorry.
قل، "أنا آسف.
I stopped observing the house for a moment,
توقفت عن مراقبة البيت للحظة،
and when I started observing again,
وحين بدأت أراقب مجددا،
everything had happened."
حدث كل شيء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's the strong anthropic principle of vacuuming.
ذاك مبدأ أنثروبي قوي للكنس.
For me, it's a very, very important thing.
بالنسبة لي، إنه أمر في غاية الأهمية.
Even on my journey up here --
حتى في رحلتي إلى هنا --
the joy that I have on my journey up here every single time.
السعادة التي أحس بها في رحلتي كل مرة إلى هنا.
If you actually think, you remove the myth and there is still something wonderful.
إن فكرتم فعلا، تزيل الأسطورة ولا يزال هناك أمر مذهل.
I'm sitting on a train.
أنا جالس في القطار.
Every time I breathe in,
في كل مرة أستنشق،
I'm breathing in a million-billion-billion
أستنشق ملايين المليارات
atoms of oxygen.
من ذرات الأوكسجين.
I'm sitting on a chair.
أنا جالس على الكرسي.
Even though I know the chair is made of atoms
وعلى الرغم من أنني أعرف أن الكرسي مصنوع من الذرات
and therefore actually in many ways empty space,
وبالتالي وفي الواقع فضاء فارغ في نواح كثيرة،
I find it comfortable.
أجده مريحا.
I look out the window, and I realize
أنظر خارج النافذة، أدرك
that every single time we stop and I look out that window,
أنه في كل مرة نتوقف وأنظر خارج النافذة،
framed in that window,
في إطار تلك النافذة،
wherever we are,
أينما كنا،
I am observing more life
أنظر إلى حياة أكثر
than there is in the rest of the known universe
مما يوجد في بقية الكون المعروف
beyond the planet Earth.
خارج كوكب الأرض.
If you go to the safari parks
إن ذهبتم إلى متنزهات السفاري
on Saturn or Jupiter,
أو زحل أو المشتري،
you will be disappointed.
سيخيب أملكم.
And I realize I'm observing this
وأدرك أنني ألاحظ هذا
with the brain, the human brain,
بدماغ، الدماغ البشري،
the most complex thing in the known universe.
أكثر شيء معقد في الكون المعلوم.
That, to me, is an incredible thing.
ذلك، بالنسبة لي، هو أمر مدهش.
And do you know what, that might be enough.
وتعرفون ماذا، ذاك قد يكون كافيا.
Steven Weinberg, the Nobel laureate, once said,
ستيفن واينبرغ، الحائز على جائزة نوبل، قال ذات مرة،
"The more the universe seems comprehensible,
"كلما بدا الكون مفهوما أكثر،
the more it seems pointless."
بدا غير ذي نفع أكثر."
Now for some people,
الآن بالنسبة لبعض الناس،
that seems to lead to an idea of nihilism.
يبدو أن ذلك يقود إلى فكرة عدمية.
But for me, it doesn't. That is a wonderful thing.
لكن بالنسبة لي، لا يفعل. ذلك أمر مذهل.
I'm glad the universe is pointless.
أنا مسرور لأن الكون غير ذي نفع.
It means if I get to the end of my life,
بمعنى إن وصلت آخر حياتي،
the universe can't turn to me and go, "What have you been doing, you idiot?
لن يخاطبني الكون قائلا، "ما الذي كنت تفعله، أيها الأبله؟
That's not the point."
ليس ذلك هو القصد."
I can make my own purpose.
أستطيع أن أضع غايتي الخاصة.
You can make your own purpose.
يمكنك أن تضع غايتك الخاصة.
We have the individual power
لدينا القوة الفردية
to go, "This is what I want to do."
في أن نقول، "هذا ما أريد القيام به."
And in a pointless universe, that, to me, is a wonderful thing.
وفي كون غير ذي نفع، ذلك، بالنسبة لي، أمر مذهل.
I have chosen to make silly jokes
اخترت أن أقدم نكتا سخيفة
about quantum mechanics and the Copenhagen interpretation.
عن ميكانيكا الكم وتفسير كوبنهاجن.
You, I imagine, can do much better things with your time.
أتصور أنكم تستطيعون القيام بأمور أحسن في وقتكم.
Thank you very much. Goodbye.
شكرا جزيلا لكم. وداعا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)